Guide to the National Organization for Women, New York City Chapter (NOW-NYC) Records TAM.106
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
National Organization for Women: New York City Chapter Records
1965 - ongoing
1966-2002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
National Organization for Women. New York City
TAM.106
77.88 Linear Feet in 132 manuscript boxes, 4 half manuscript boxes, 6 record cartons, 5 flat boxes, 17 oversized flat boxes, 9 flat-file-folders, a CD box, a card box, and a cassette box
2 websites in 2 archived websites.
26 VHS
7 U-matic
12 audiocassette
3 Betamax
1 Betacam
4 1_Inch_Video_Reel
6.9 Gigabytes in 1,467 computer files.
The National Organization for Women (NOW) was established in Washington, D.C. in 1966 by Betty Friedan, with the New York City Chapter (NOW-NYC) following in 1967. The National Organization for Women: New York City Chapter Records (dated 1965-ongoing) documents the operations, activism, events, and topical interests of NOW-NYC. The collection contains organizational documentation and administrative records; conference materials; membership information; communications and publicity materials; legal and policy documentation; correspondence; subject files; ephemera; photographs; audio and video recordings; and an archived version of the New York chapter website, http://nownyc.org/.
Historical Note
In 1966, Betty Friedan founded the National Organization for Women (NOW) in Washington, D.C., a group whose goal was to "bring women into the mainstream of American society." A year later in 1967, the New York Chapter (NOW-NYC) was founded. NOW-NYC's first four presidents were Jean Faust, Ti-Grace Atkinson, Ivy Bottini, and Jacqueline Ceballos. Early organizing efforts for NOW-NYC were largely related to employment discrimination in hiring practices; and wage discrepancies between men and women. One of NOW-NYC's early victories was the elimination of sex-segregated help-wanted advertisements in the New York Times. From its inception, the group was focused on several issues and functioned through a committee structure that included committees on the arts; child care and family relations; education and employment; the image of women in the media; legislation and politics; reproductive rights; and sexuality.
Over the years, NOW-NYC organized major demonstrations and strikes, most notably the "Women Strike for Equality March" held in New York City on August 26, 1970, which became an annual tradition for the organization for several years. In its early days, NOW-NYC often used attention-grabbing tactics to amplify its visibility despite its modest size—for example, staging a "flush-in" outside Colgate-Palmolive's offices to protest discriminatory hiring practices. Alongside these creative protests, NOW-NYC also employed more conventional democratic strategies such as lobbying legislators, gathering petitions, and sending mass mailings to the White House in an attempt to influence government policy. NOW-NYC later joined NOW-New York State (NOW-NYS) in hosting an annual state lobbying day; and during the 1980s, the organization established the WomanPower PAC, a political action committee dedicated to raising funds to help elect women and feminist candidates to public office.
During the 1970s, NOW-NYC's Education Committee examined course selections available to girls and boys in New York Public School and the committee's findings, "Report on Sex Bias in the Public Schools," prompted curriculum changes in schools nationwide. By the mid-1970s, NOW-NYC established one of the first Rape Prevention Committees that focused on issues related to sexual violence against women. This committee provided a range of services to survivors of rape and battery, while also helping to shift public attitudes toward these crimes and their victims. In the late 1970s and throughout the 1980s, NOW-NYC expanded its employment initiatives to include career-training workshops and job referral programs for both employees and employers
In the early 1970s, as the campaign to pass the Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) began and gathered significant momentum throughout the decade, particularly in the years leading up to the ratification deadline, the ERA became a primary focus for NOW-NYC. NOW-NYC's ERA Task Force collaborated with activists in other states to support ratification efforts in state legislatures. In addition to its political advocacy, NOW-NYC's Image Committee worked to promote fair and respectful portrayals of women in the arts and media. This committee played a role in influencing changes to print advertising, while the Arts Committee highlighted gender discrimination within the art world.
As of 2025, NOW-NYC continues its mission to advance equality for women in New York City.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 13 series, with one series being further arranged into subseries. Most series have been arranged alphabetically by topic and then further arranged chronologically, when applicable. General correspondence found in Series II is arranged in chronological order, while correspondence with specific subjects are arranged in alphabetical order after the general correspondence. Series VI: National and Regional NOW is first arranged by chapter or region, starting with the largest organizing group to smallest, and then topics are arranged alphabetically.
The collection is arranged as follows:
Series I: Administration
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Officers' Files
Subseries III.A: Jean Faust
Subseries III.B: Elayne Snyder
Subseries III.C: Noreen Connell
Subseries III.D: Matthea Marquart
Series IV: Committees
Series V: Programs and Events
Series VI: National and Regional NOW
Series VII: NOW and other Organizations
Series VIII: Photographs, Negatives, and Slides
Series IX: Artifacts, Ephemera, and Graphic Materials
Series X: Our North American Foremothers Documentary
Series XI: Audiovisual Materials
Series XII: Legal Cases
Series XIII: Archived Website
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by NOW-NYC in 1978, 1981-1993, 2008, 2012, 2018, 2023, and 2025. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1981.007, 1981.008, 1981.010, 2008.062, 2012.069, 2016.042, 2018.019, 2023.097 and 2025.082.
Materials found in the repository were added to the collection in 2014, 2015, and 2017. The accession number associated with these materials are 2014.054, NPA 2000.216, NPA 2000.232, NPA 2001.023, NPA 2000.208 and NPA 2000.209
https://nownyc.org/ was initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2007 as part of the Other Left Activism Web Archive. In 2014, http://nownyc-notcool.tumblr.com/ was added. In November 2015, these websites were migrated to Archive-It, which uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy from the resulting WARC file of the website. In February 2022, seven Google Documents related to the 2021 Manhattan District Attorney candidates were added to Archive-it to better capture these materials directly. The accession numbers associated with these websites are 2022.043.
Scope and Contents
The National Organization for Women: New York City Chapter Records (inclusive dates 1965-ongoing; bulk dates 1966-2002) documents the administrative operations of NOW-NYC, the chapter's committees, the Service Fund of NOW-NYC, the Legal Defense and Education Fund, WomanPower PAC, and other regional branches of NOW; activism including Marches on Washington on behalf of women's rights, the Equality Riders Campaigns on behalf of the Equal Rights Amendment (ERA), and legal assistance offered through the Womanpower Project to women facing sexual discrimination in the workplace; and events including the Susan B. Anthony Awards, Women of Power and Influence Awards, National NOW conferences, the ERA Walk-A-Thon, and Opening New Doors: A Sales Career Conference for Women. This collection also documents the topical interests of the NOW-NYC including reproductive rights, sexual discrimination, media depictions of women, family relations, domestic violence, and the ERA. Materials in this collection are in paper, analog audiovisual, and electronic format.
The collection contains board, membership, and committee meeting minutes; administrative documents such as bylaws, agendas, calendars, memorandum, officers' files, treasurer's reports, committee reports, membership information, voting records, resumes, job descriptions, and budgets. The collection also includes correspondence between members of NOW-NYC, politicians, affiliated groups, legal organizations, and the media; conference materials such as agendas, programs, and information packets; communications and publicity materials including newsletters, press releases, pamphlets, event flyers, posters, and press clippings; legal and policy documentation including government publications, legislative bills, court decisions, legal briefs, and depositions; ephemera including pins, protest signs, banners, posters, and songbooks; photographs documenting NOW-NYC protests, special events, and award ceremonies; and audio and video recordings of NOW-NYC sponsored protests, conferences, symposiums, and other events. The collection also contains subject files, covering a variety of topics including, but not limited to: abortion, rape, domestic violence, marriage, divorce, child care, the 1984 Presidential election, non-traditional jobs for women, education access for women, how to manage finances, reproductive rights, problematic media portrayal of women, and the women's liberation movement.
An archived version of NOW-NYC's website, http://nownyc.org/, is also included in the collection. The website was first captured in 2007. The website includes information on the latest news and events regarding NOW-NYC, their priorities, and ways to get involved.
Researchers are advised that this collection contains two photographs that include nudity and depict death. These photographs are identified in the folder inventory of Series VIII: Photographs, Negatives, and Slides.
Legacy description, which may include outdated terminology, has been left in place.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Separated Materials
Feminist newsletters and newspapers have been removed from the collection and rehoused as part of the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Women's Rights Serials (TAM 751). They fall into the following categories: National NOW newsletters; NOW Regional newsletters (East, West, etc.); NOW--New York State newsletters; Local chapters of NOW (excluding NOW New York Chapter); NOW New York Chapter newsletters; and NOW New York Chapter committee newsletters.
Copies of Majority Report: The Women's Newspaper, Majority Report: The Women's Newspaper, New Directions for Women, and The NOW York Woman were removed from the collection because they are catalogued and searchable in New York University's Library catalog system.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Audiovisual materials that have not been preserved may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact NYU Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for the purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Custodial History
During the initial processing of the National Organization for Women: New York City Chapter Records, photographs, ephemera, artifacts, and audio recordings were separated and cataloged as the National Organization for Women: New York City Chapter Photographs (PHOTOS 081) and the National Organization for Women: New York City Chapter Oral History Collection (OH 044). Posters were also removed and incorporated into the Tamiment Library Poster and Broadside Collection (GRAPHICS 002), under the subseries US56.2 - Women/National Organization for Women. Audiovisual materials were transferred to the library's film collection at this time.
In 2014, all of the separated materials were reintegrated into the National Organization for Women: New York City Chapter Records (TAM 106); NOW-NYC's archived website, preserved through the Internet Archive's Archive-It service, was added as Series XIII: Archived Website; and approximately 0.25 linear feet of additional materials found within the repository were incorporated into the collection, primarily within Series VI: National and Regional NOW.
Appraisal
During the course of processing in Fall 2025, the following materials were removed from the collection: duplicate materials; official employment complaints and legal materials protected under attorney-client privilege; materials containing social security numbers, resumes, and other personal identifying information; and off air recordings and commercially available films.
In November 2025, three 1" open reel videos with duplicative content were deaccessioned.
Missing Materials
Some recordings from Series XI: Audiovisual Materials are missing as of October 2019 and are therefore not available to researchers.
Press releases.; 16mm; Résumés (personnel records); Reports.; Contact sheets.; Day care centers -- United States.; Abortion -- United States; Clippings (information artifacts); Negatives (photographic); New York (N.Y.).; Feminism -- New York (State) -- New York.; Minutes (administrative records); Photographic prints.; Posters.; Newsletters.; Pamphlets.; Women -- Political activity -- United States.; Women -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Scripts (documents); Slides (photographs); Women's rights -- New York (State) -- New York.; Briefs (legal documents); Press releases.; Posters.; Banners.; Minutes (administrative records); Memorandums.; VHS; Audiocassettes.; Sex discrimination in employment.; Equal rights amendments; Chisholm, Shirley, 1924-2005; Brademas, John, 1927-2016; Steinem, Gloria; WBAI Radio (New York, N.Y.); Abzug, Bella S., 1920-1998; Dean, John W. (John Wesley), 1938-; Griffins, Martha; Javits, Jacob K. (Jacob Koppel), 1904-1986; Koch, Ed, 1924-2013; McGovern, George S. (George Stanley), 1922-2012; Mink, Patsy T., 1927-2002; Muskie, Edward; National Organization for Women. New York City
- Series I: Administration, 1966-2011; 1971-2002; 13.08 Linear Feet in 25 manuscript boxes, a half manuscript box, and 3 oversized flat boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Materials found in this series provide insight into NOW-NYC's organizational structure, how it functions as a whole, and the type of administrative tasks undertaken by this chapter. This series includes meeting minutes, agendas, memoranda, bylaws, job descriptions, press releases, administrative procedures, notes, budgets, elections materials, and calendars. Materials providing an overview of both NOW and NOW-NYC's history can also be found in this series.
  Arrangement
  Materials in this series are arranged alphabetically by topic and then chronologically, if applicable.
  Historical Note
  The Executive Committee consists of the following officers: President, Vice President, Secretary, and Treasurer; the Board of Directors consists of officers and standing committee coordinators; and the Advisory Council is an administrative committee whose purpose is to assist with fund raising and chapter development. The Elections Committee is an administrative committee whose purpose is to organize and conduct elections.
  - Action Alert Mailings, 2000-2001 (Box 105, Folder 2)
  - Action Center, 2001 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Address Book, undated (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Administrative Director Manual, 2002 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Advisory Committee -- Child Care Meeting, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Council, 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Affiliation Forms, undated (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports, 1998-2001 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Appointment Book, 1986 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Blank NOW-NYC Administrative Forms, undated (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors Directories and Information, 1968-1997, 2000-2002 (Box 28, Folder 8-9)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1967 (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 11)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3, Box 28, Folder 12)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4, Box 28, Folder 13)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5, Box 28, Folder 14)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6, Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9, Box 30, Folder 2-4)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10, Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11, Box 30, Folder 6-7)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12, Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 13, Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14, Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 15, Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16, Box 31, Folder 4-6)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17, Box 32, Folder 1-4)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1985 (Box 32, Folder 5-6)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1986 (Box 32, Folder 7, Box 48, Folder 1-3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1987 (Box 48, Folder 4-5, Box 49, Folder 1-3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1988 (Box 49, Folder 4-5)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1989 (Box 50, Folder 1-2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, January 1989 - August 1989 (Box 1A, Folder 1-2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, September 1989 - December 1989 (Box 1A, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1990 (Box 50, Folder 3-4)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, January 1990 - November 1990 (Box 1A, Folder 4-5)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1991 (Box 50, Folder 5, Box 51, Folder 1-2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1992 (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1993 (Box 51, Folder 4-5)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1994 (Box 51, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1995 (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1996 (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1997 (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1997-1998 (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1998-1999 (Box 52, Folder 5-6)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1999-2000 (Box 52, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1999-2005 (Box 158, Folder 1, Box 46)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 2000 (Box 52, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 2000-2001 (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 2001 (Box 53, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 2002 (Box 53, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 2003 (Box 53, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, undated (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - Board Orientation Information, 1984-1985 (Box 53, Folder 6)
  - Burglary at NOW-NYC, 1977 (Box 53, Folder 7)
  - Bylaws, 1966-1978, 1986, 1996, 2000, 2002 (Box 1A, Folder 7, Box 53, Folder 8-9)
  - Calendars, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Calendars, 1974, 1976, 1992-1993, 2001 (Box 53, Folder 10, Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Calendars, 1975-1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chapter Actions, undated (Box 53, Folder 11)
  - Chapter Development Day, 1989, 1993, 1999-2001 (Box 53, Folder 12)
  - Chapter Fundraising Information Packet, undated (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - Charter, 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Choosing an Action" Guidelines, undated (Box 54, Folder 2)
  - Committee Bulletin Board, 1971 (Box 54, Folder 3)
  - Committee Coordinator Guidelines, 1980, 1986 (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - Committee Overviews, undated (Box 54, Folder 5)
  - Conflict Resolution for NOW Chapters, undated (Box 54, Folder 6)
  - Contract [Labor] District 65 UAW and NOW NYC, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3A, Box 1)
  - Contract with Don Ramer, 1978 (Box 54, Folder 7)
  - Coordinator's Committee Meeting Minutes, 1980 (Box 54, Folder 8)
  - Coordinators Rap, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Council Meetings, 1987-1989 (Box 103, Folder 1-2)
  - Council Meetings, 1990 (Box 103, Folder 3)
  - Council Meetings, 1991-1992 (Box 103, Folder 4-5)
  - Council Meetings, 1993-1996 (Box 103, Folder 6)
  - Council Meetings, 1997 (Box 104, Folder 1-2)
  - Council Meetings, 1998 (Box 104, Folder 3-4)
  - Council Meetings, 1999-2002 (Box 104, Folder 5-6)
  - Council Meetings, 2006 (Box 104, Folder 7)
  - Council Meetings, 2007 (Box 104, Folder 8-9)
  - Election Committee, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Election Committee, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Election Committee, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Election Committee, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Election Committee, 1975-1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Establishment of New NOW-NYC Center, 1973 (Box 54, Folder 9)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Executive Meeting Agendas, 1985-1986 (Box 54, Folder 10)
  - Fact Sheets, undated (Box 54, Folder 11)
  - FBI Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) Files about NOW-NYC, 1974-1977 (Box 54, Folder 12)
  - Fundraising, 1972, 2002 (Box 54, Folder 13)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - General Membership Minutes, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)